<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2012 Hippo.
  
  This file is part of HST PDF Renderer.
  
  HST PDF Renderer is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it 
  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free 
  Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) 
  any later version.
  
  HST PDF Renderer is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but 
  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY 
  or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  See the GNU General Public License for more details.
  
  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
  HST PDF Renderer. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN" "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>HST PDF Renderer</title>
  </properties>
  <body>

    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>
        <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> basically transforms HTML output into PDF output.
        It leverages <a href="http://code.google.com/p/flying-saucer/" target="_blank">Flying Saucer</a> library to generate PDF output.
        Because Flying Saucer requires valid XHTML input for PDF generation,
        <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> supports transformation from HTML markups to valid XHTML markups 
        by leveraging <a href="http://jtidy.sourceforge.net" target="_blank">JTidy</a> library.
        HST PDF Renderer also supports a servlet filter which transforms normal HTML output to PDF output at runtime.
      </p>

      <subsection name="License">
        <p>
          <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> is provided under the terms of the <strong>GNU General Public License</strong>,
          as Flying Saucer is. See the following for detail.
        </p>
        <div class="brush: plain; gutter: false; toolbar: false;">
        <source><![CDATA[
 HST PDF Renderer is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it 
 under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free 
 Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) 
 any later version.
 
 HST PDF Renderer is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but 
 WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY 
 or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
 See the GNU General Public License for more details.
 
 You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
 HST PDF Renderer. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.
        ]]></source>
        </div>
      </subsection>

    </section>

    <section name="Project Status">
      <p>
        For the latest version, see the <a href="release-notes.html">Release notes</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Architecture">

      <p>
        <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> contains a servlet filter named 'HtmlPDFRenderingFilter' 
        which transforms HTML output from the SITE application into PDF output.
        In the following sections, you will see a typical deployment view in a web application and a runtime view
        which shows how its components are interacting at runtime.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Deployment View">
        <img src="images/deployview.png" alt="Deployment View"/>
        <ul>
          <li>Basically <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> is deployed inside a web site application (which is deployed onto a servlet container).</li>
          <li>
            You should configure the servlet filter ("HstPDFRenderingFilter") of <strong>HST PDF Renderer</strong> and its servlet filter mapping
            in order to activate the automatic PDF generation from the normal html output at runtime.
          </li>
          <li>
            You should configure CSS file(s) for HstPDFRenderingFilter.
            The CSS file(s) are used when generating PDF output, so you can customize the CSS files for your tastes.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Runtime View">
        <img src="images/cncview.png" alt="Runtime View"/>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The servlet filter, <strong>HstPDFRenderingFilter</strong>, should be located before the other rendering filters such as <strong>HstFilter</strong>.
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>HstPDFRenderingFilter</strong> invokes the filterChain to invoke the remaining servlet filtr chain
            and captures all the HTML response output.
          </li>
          <li>
            Then <strong>HstPDFRenderingFilter</strong> invokes <strong>HtmlPDFRenderer</strong>, which contains all the core logic
            for XHTML transformation and PDF generation.
            (Note: <strong>HtmlPDFRenderer</strong> can be used separately, even in a stand-alone application.)
          </li>
          <li>
            Then <strong>HtmlPDFRenderer</strong> cleans up the captured HTML output and transforms it to valid XHTML output,
            by leveraging <strong>JTidy</strong> library (org.w3c.tidy.*).
          </li>
          <li>
            Finally <strong>HtmlPDFRenderer</strong> invokes <strong>Flying Saucer</strong> library (org.xhtmlrenderer.*)
            in order to generate PDF output. The PDF output is sent to the user agent through <strong>HstPDFRenderingFilter</strong> in the end.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

    </section>

    <section name="Running Demo Application">
      <subsection name="Check out demo application">
        <p>
          Fork me on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/onehippo-forge/hst-pdf-renderer" target="_blank">https://github.com/onehippo-forge/hst-pdf-renderer</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Build the project using Maven:
        </p>
        <div class="brush: bash">
        <source>$ mvn install</source>
        </div>
        <p>And, build and run the demo in the <code>demo</code> subfolder.</p>
        <div class="brush: bash">
        <source><![CDATA[
$ cd demo
$ mvn clean package
$ mvn -P cargo.run
        ]]></source>
        </div>
        <p>
          Try to click PDF icon button on each detail page in the website, http://localhost:8080/site/.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
